<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Technology and Choice</title>
    <description>Redfrost Jekyll boilerplate</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 19:36:53 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 19:36:53 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technology and Choice (What&#39;s in a Name?)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;[Note: link to author’s reading of the article appears at the bottom of the article]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology and Choice&lt;/em&gt; is a great name for a podcast, don’t you think? A lot of people seem to find the title compelling, all by itself. I know I do. There’s so much implied, yet so formlessly. Even I only have a vague idea of where we’re going with this–just a thread to start pulling, really. So, why is the name so engaging?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choice&quot;&gt;Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice is one of those weird strings the universe leaves hanging out. Pull on it and secrets that have been hidden in plain sight start to fall and hit the ground with a resounding “Duh!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas choices are things &lt;em&gt;you have&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;you do,&lt;/em&gt; choice at its highest level is something that &lt;em&gt;you are;&lt;/em&gt; it’s of your nature. We won’t dwell on this too much here, other than to say that as individuals, we are inseparable from Choice. Can’t dodge it, can’t choose not to choose. But while I feel that contemplating this fact is both interesting and efficacious, I don’t plan to beat folks over the head with it too much. We’ll get down to more mundane matters in a moment. However . . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-water-alert&quot;&gt;Deep Water Alert!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really not sure how deep this goes but I suspect that it goes to the very nature of all human experience, and perhaps even to the core of the whole universe. I am sure that these are not new thoughts or avenues of examination. I just haven’t seen them approached in this way, and I think it will be an adventure to just poke around for ourselves without asking permission. I only mention my suspicion about how deep it goes as an aside to inform you of my depth of interest, and perhaps audacity. The ultimate nature and character of Who or What does the choosing can be set aside for the moment. But the bottom line is that if you have a sense of self, &lt;em&gt;you DO choose,&lt;/em&gt; so you have a direct stake in what we’re talking about, and a full share of responsibility, as well. Beyond that, let’s see if we can use what we do know and experience to pull apart the rest, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technology&quot;&gt;Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When launching the Technology and Choice podcast, the initial definition of technology being worked with was something like “the formalized application of knowledge and information to do things.” That’s a fairly inclusive definition, but the more we worked with this pair of ideas, the clearer things have become, and a better definition presents itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology is a patterned system of choices—”if this, then that”—put into action to accomplish things in various circumstances.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a much tidier definition because it relates it to something that each of us has undeniable experience with and thus responsibility for (i.e., choice), but also it encompasses the whole scope of technology from stone axes to home economics to computers and the rest of the high tech marvels from here on out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that wraps it up, then, right? We can all go home now! Yeah, sure. If life were that simple, it would be boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Because technologies build on other technologies (choice patterns incorporate other, already established, choice patterns) the origins of the choices and the intentions of the technologies involved become quite an interesting tangle. This tangle tends to displace responsibility further and further from the individual choices made in the moment to choices made in the past by indefinite “others.” Thus does the question “Who moved my cheese?” become an interesting but often unsolvable problem. Or might it be the wrong question? What fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could still be very hard-nosed and say, “You choose, so no excuses! Fess up, take responsibility and take your lumps!” While there’s probably a lot more truth in such an attitude than we might wish to admit, there’s no subtlety there. Isn’t it, maybe, a bit more complicated than that? I mean, if I’m going to confess to something, I really prefer to have a decent idea of what’s going on, you know? Good! That gives us a good reason to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s examine &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;choices&lt;/em&gt; a bit deeper, on a bit more practical, everyday-experience level and see if it sheds some light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types-and-facets-of-choice&quot;&gt;Types and Facets of Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.safecrossroads.net/articles/the-decentralization-itch-3/&quot;&gt;The Decentralization Itch&lt;/a&gt; is an article I published last year on safecrossroads.net and the Let’s Talk Bitcoin network. In it I show pretty irrefutably how choice is something that only Self can do, because that’s where you look to find free will, volition, etc. While that logic is rock solid, I think, the patterns and packages of choices, and the complexities of life can make the truth of that logic hard to track and thus easy to doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not trying to make any sweeping conclusions here. We’re just tinkering with the stuff of life itself, after all. But we can take a closer look at some of the different forms choice takes in day-to-day life and see how it affects our view of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the simpler, more straightforward types:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analytical choice&lt;/strong&gt; – There are various tools one can apply to refine the process of making an analytical choice, but it is basically a matter of applying evaluation of data and reason to arrive at the best solution in a given situation, and then choosing that course. This is the type of choice from which we structure our more rational, considered modes of behavior. It is also the type of choice a programmer uses to encode choice patterns in software, or an engineer uses to build choice patterns into a machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gut, instinctive or intuitive choices&lt;/strong&gt; – While much could probably be said about each of these separately, we can group them together as choices which result from factors outside conscious analysis, such as subconscious perception, bred-in response to stimuli, etc., whether accurate or false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotional/reactive choices&lt;/strong&gt; – Such choices may or may not be rational or appropriate to the situation in which they arise. They may be in-the-moment, or come out of current response to prior experience, or even past trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Habit pattern choices&lt;/strong&gt; – These are preprogrammed choice patterns that go into effect in certain circumstances. Sometimes these are desirable and effective (good habits), and sometimes they are undesirable and inappropriate (bad habits). Habits result from conscious choices which are adopted into patterns of behavior, both on an individual level, and interactively in groups of individuals. Habits are also trained in by upbringing. Others are enforced by schooling (which is different than education).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s consider some more involved choice patterns that really start to complicate and obscure responsibility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More involved sets of “if this, then that” agreements or operations&lt;/strong&gt; – This is a very broad category encompassing pretty much anything from rule books, to computer programs, to operating instructions, to contracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Agreements, explicit or implied&lt;/strong&gt; – I sometimes think that we live in the world or worlds that conform to the user agreements we’ve tacitly accepted, with just about the same amount of consideration for what those user agreements say as when we blithely say that we have read and understand the user agreements on any particular website today. What more could there be to say on this one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social-contract/social-proof choices&lt;/strong&gt; – These are choices  individuals make to be in agreement with a group, perhaps considering that there is some wisdom or a not-understood system at work, or simply not wishing to stand out. In the case of social contract, such choices may arise from the concept that one owes a duty of subservience to an authority in exchange for just rulership. Such choices may or may not be rational, depending upon the scene, but there is a strong tendency to assume the imperative of group behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Definition: &lt;strong&gt;Social proof&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as &lt;strong&gt;informational social influence&lt;/strong&gt;, is a psychological phenomenon where people assume the actions of others in an attempt to reflect correct behavior for a given situation. This effect is prominent in ambiguous social situations where people are unable to determine the appropriate mode of behavior, and is driven by the assumption that surrounding people possess more knowledge about the situation. – Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pledge of allegiance fits pretty well here. Who even really considers what it actually means, especially when you start being required to chant it as a child with no idea what it means?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, speaking of children and choice, we learn a huge portion of our lifetime lessons when we’re children, through social-proof-type circumstances. Seems to me that it would be a responsible thing to do to take up such things very purposefully and decide carefully whether those patterns of decision are really valid or not. If they are, then we can subscribe to them anew, with the full weight of our considered adult responsibility. If they are not valid, we’d best revoke them and try to take responsibility for any errors we’ve made while believing they were valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an early age, I showed that I wasn’t too prone to conform to social proof. For example, when I was about 11, in a Boy Scout meeting one evening, we were doing drills. The order was “left face” and I turned to what I was certain was the left. Everyone else turned the opposite direction. I was surprised that everyone else could be so mistaken and stayed with my choice. Well, after a few seconds I grudging turned to “their” left and got back in sync. I did have to admit that I had gotten it wrong, but I never lost the pride of having continued to turn to the direction I thought was correct, despite the rest doing otherwise. I’ve always been a bit cheeky that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure we could lay out plenty of other flavors of choice which have interesting aspects and twists, but that gives us enough to get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technology-and-the-everything-else&quot;&gt;Technology and the Everything Else&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer programming is one of the best examples of prepackaging choices in a pattern. “If this circumstance exists, apply that algorithm, etc.” This concept of patterned choices applies at a very basic level. It’s a package of choices and we invoke it to accomplish certain things. We don’t like it if the program also does things (behind the curtain so to speak) that we don’t approve of. Thus the great appeal and security advantages of the open source software movement, and the up and coming open hardware movement, as well. The choices are all out there in the open where people can see them. Maybe I won’t have the foggiest idea how to read code, or know the implications even if I could read it, but I know that others can read and understand. I can see what a bunch of independent people say, and then make a reasonably informed choice as to what will happen when I use the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great example is the engineering design and construction of a complex machine or set of machines. “If this, then that” built right into physical forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to think of these sorts of things with a capital “T”. Technology is those choice packages we have enshrined in physical machines, devices and systems, or a least put down as discrete systems of instruction in books and manuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more chaotic patterns of choice we see operating in life and society and random human interaction don’t really rise to the level of Technology. Or do they? The thing is, I’m not so sure there is a clear line separating one from the other, in anything but a very arbitrary way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe our understanding of the more codified patterns of choice which we think of as Technology can help us better understand and refine the more uncharted, but very real and persistent, patterns in our social and economic interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, from the other end, maybe examination of the anarcho-factual &lt;em&gt;[see below]&lt;/em&gt; choices and choice patterns of individuals, in the wild and untidy world at large, can help us better appreciate and more appropriately use the tidier end of the scale which we call Technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, it’s all of a piece . . . isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;anarcho-factual:&lt;/strong&gt; (term coined by the author) &lt;em&gt;anarcho&lt;/em&gt; = “no ruler,” &lt;em&gt;factual&lt;/em&gt; = “in truth.” I don’t pretend to know with certainty all about the best form which society should take, and I would not seek to force such on others. “Anarchy” is a political philosophy which holds that society is best formed by voluntary association rather than using political force. By contrast, my perspective is that society IS formed by the choices of individuals. There factually are no rulers superior to individual choice, except as individuals assign or accept them. I think that when enough people take responsibility for the truth of this fact, and pattern their choices accordingly, a better society will emerge, whatever form it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published
Copyleft&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by
John Ferguson
18 April 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/259627230&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/04/technology-and-choice-whats-in-a-name/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/04/technology-and-choice-whats-in-a-name/</guid>
        
        <category>article</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Episode 3 - The Resounding Duh!</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/259650539&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-this-episode&quot;&gt;In this Episode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to read and/or listen to the article “Technology and Choice (What’s in a Name?)”. The title of this episode will make more sense once you’ve read the article or listened to this episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discuss the substance of that article from some different angles. We have some fun, and even start bleeding into next episode’s topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music for this episode: &lt;em&gt;SafeProject,&lt;/em&gt; an original piece composed and performed by Nicholas Koteskey of Two Faced Heroes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://letstalkbitcoin.com/blog/post/technology-and-choice-article-whats-in-a-name&quot;&gt;Technology and Choice (What’s in a Name?) article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.safecrossroads.net/articles/the-decentralization-itch-3/&quot;&gt;The Decentralization Itch article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/safecrossroads/the-decentralization-itch&quot;&gt;The Decentralization Itch article audio reading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://livsensical.com/scamfree&quot;&gt;Scam Free ebook–prep for next episode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/04/episode-3-the-resounding-duh/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/04/episode-3-the-resounding-duh/</guid>
        
        <category>podcast</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Episode 2 - Revenge of the Social Media Zombies</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/256950129&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-this-episode&quot;&gt;In this Episode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s up with social media and what does it have to do with zombies? You’ll just have to listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music for this episode: &lt;em&gt;SafeProject,&lt;/em&gt; an original piece composed and performed by Nicholas Koteskey of Two Faced Heroes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://selfhelpbook.midwestjournalpress.com/&quot;&gt;Midwest Journal Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://safecrossroads.net&quot;&gt;Crossroads of Project SAFE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://livesensical.com/podcast/selling-books-online/revenge-social-media-zombies/&quot;&gt;Revenge of the Social Media Zombies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20160313-the-unstoppable-rise-of-the-facebook-dead&quot;&gt;Facebook is a growing and unstoppable digital graveyard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://contentmarketinginstitute.com/2015/11/content-creation-facebook-podcast/&quot;&gt;Facebook becoming lurkers - 66% report not posting in three months&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/246777&quot;&gt;The truth about Facebook and Millenials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://contentmarketinginstitute.com/2016/03/social-media-content-podcast/&quot;&gt;Google allowing celebrities and businesses post directly to keywords&lt;/a&gt;–minute 8:30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://contentmarketinginstitute.com/2016/03/social-media-content-podcast/&quot;&gt;Google evangelist Avniash Kaushik asks people to subscribe to his newsletter as Google is restricting organic content&lt;/a&gt; –minute 29:13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2016/03/20/the-death-of-instagram-for-brands/?ncid=rss&quot;&gt;Instagram updated newsfeed to limit organic reach - in favor of ads. {Facebook owns.}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.breitbart.com/big-government/2013/09/24/53-of-obama-twitter-followers-are-fake-accounts/&quot;&gt;Fake twitter followers–&amp;gt; Obama - 53% fake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vocativ.com/news/239402/which-presidential-candidates-have-the-most-fake-twitter-followers/&quot;&gt;Presidential candidates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gizmodo.com/5994621/which-celebrities-have-the-most-fake-twitter-followers&quot;&gt;Celebrity fakes–Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/celebrities-with-the-most-fake-facebook-likes-2012-9&quot;&gt;Celebrity fakes–Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifttt.com/&quot;&gt;IFTTT–If This Then That&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gigaom.com/2011/06/24/419-what-shoppers-dont-realize-about-amazons-reviews/&quot;&gt;Amazon’s DIrty Laundry of Reviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nautil.us/issue/12/feedback/one-percenters-control-online-reviews&quot;&gt;Only 1.5% naturally write reviews, 1 in 15 reviewers never bought that product&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://livesensical.com/podcast/live-sensical/revenge-bucket-crabs-become-follow/&quot;&gt;5% make it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flipboard.com/@robertworst2015/author-preneur-55nhr5lqy&quot;&gt;Author-preneur on Flipboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/04/episode-2-revenge-of-the-social-media-zombies/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/04/episode-2-revenge-of-the-social-media-zombies/</guid>
        
        <category>podcast</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Episode 1 - Virtual Reality</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/256036073&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-this-episode&quot;&gt;In this Episode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the first episode of Technology and Choice, the podcast where we’re likely to talk about almost anything, as long as it centers around these two concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we introduce ourselves (John and Robert) and lay the groundwork for the ongoing podcast. Then we take up the subject of Virtual Reality technology, how it’s starting to take its place in the world, as well as what choices it makes possible, and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music for this episode: &lt;em&gt;SafeProject,&lt;/em&gt; an original piece composed and performed by Nicholas Koteskey of Two Faced Heroes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vroxygen.io&quot;&gt;VR Oxygen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://selfhelpbook.midwestjournalpress.com/&quot;&gt;Midwest Journal Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://livesensical.com&quot;&gt;Live Sensical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://safecrossroads.net&quot;&gt;Crossroads of Project SAFE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Referenced novels by Neal Stephenson (wonderful in audio)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The Diamond Age” and “Snow Crash”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/03/episode-1-virtual-reality/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/03/episode-1-virtual-reality/</guid>
        
        <category>podcast</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Decentralization Itch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Decentralization.&lt;/em&gt; The buzzword of our times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing numbers and types of people are possessed of an elusive, but very real, visceral “itch” tied to the concept of decentralization. It’s hard to tell if the itch is caused by the concept or if the concept is simply being deployed in an effort to scratch the itch. It can have the appearance of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Decentralization, good; centralization, bad.” We see more and more sectors of society plugging this idea into their thoughts and conversations in whatever way it can be made to fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologists in many fields talk about the need to decentralize systems. After all, the original strength of and reason for instituting the Internet was that decentralization would allow communications to continue, even in the event of nuclear war. The decentralization push is going forward on an increasing number of fronts, including power generation and distribution, food production and distribution, 3D printing, localized manufacturing, and the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both extreme ends of the liberal-to-conservative political spectrum talk about more decentralization of power, at least on their own pet issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of the cryptographic-currency movement is largely driven by a desire to take the control of money out of the hands of the centralized, powerful few, who seem destined to corruption, even if some don’t start out that way. Also, existing financial systems are suffering severe scaling and security issues. Decentralizing currency offers at least one mitigation of both of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most radical express their frustration as “Decentralize Everything!” This phrase has even started to appear prominently in graffiti-art for social change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is as if people from all different corners of humanity are catching this itch, and the concept of decentralization kind of, sort of scratches it. But thinking and talking about decentralization don’t quite make the itch go away. On the contrary, they just make it come back even stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-whats-under-the-skin&quot;&gt;So What’s Under the Skin?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, myself, have been worrying this itch for a while now, and have been frustrated by the sense that there’s something there, right on the edge of perception, that needs to be clearly viewed and effectively communicated about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as I often do when I need to sort out something like this, I went to the dictionary (and beyond) to find out if what I’m trying to give expression to has already been said somewhere and is all wrapped up. The fascinating thing about this particular itch is that what I’m glimpsing isn’t clearly touched upon in any place that I can find, at least not in any talk of decentralization. But definition is almost always a great place to start, so here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the prefix de- means “reverse of” or “away from,” let’s start with the root concept:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Centralization&lt;/strong&gt; is the process by which the activities of an organization, particularly those regarding planning and decision-making, become concentrated within a particular location and/or group, or keeping all of the important &lt;strong&gt;decision-making powers&lt;/strong&gt; within head office or the center of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Wikipedia [emphasis added]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve checked quite a few references and none varies in any important way from this definition, and from this we can isolate the important kernel, which is of course “decision-making powers.” This is the &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; which is being centralized or decentralized: the power of decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. So now we’ve got a core &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; to talk about: Decision or, synonymously, Choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One fact I find very curious is that all discussions, dissertations and analyses that I’ve been able to find about decentralization have dealt with the concept only from within presupposed sets of assumptions: i.e., structure of government, structure of organizations, structure of communications systems, etc. Nowhere is there a clear examination of the characteristics of the thing being dealt with, or how its nature might affect the problems being considered, or even the questions being asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision. . . . Choice, centralization or decentralization of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mysticism&quot;&gt;Mysticism?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lest we get tangled up debating metaphysical opinions, let’s ground out the conversation right here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you read or hear my words in this moment, do you have a sense of what I mean when I say “you”? If you can think “&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; understand,” or even, “Does he actually think he’s somehow talking to &lt;strong&gt;me&lt;/strong&gt;?” then you are laying hands solidly on the only datum needed to take the next logical step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t even need to know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; you are to have the sense &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; you are, so we can bypass any arguments about our ultimate nature. Another way of saying this is that you have a sense of Self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you’ll probably agree that though this idea may give you a mystical feeling, it’s a solid reality that you really can’t avoid, even by asserting that your sense of Self is an illusion. Maybe it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; illusion, but the sense persists, does it not? You still have to assert your existence to say, “&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; don’t exist” — an obvious contradiction. It is wondrous to behold how strongly some will forcefully exert their own existence in order to assert their own non-existence. But for our purposes here, we can set all that head banging aside, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re not talking about something out in some distant theoretical realm. We’re talking about something with which you have the most intimate experience, and thus the most empowered position to judge. We are talking about the fact that all of our experience revolves around our sense of Self, and thus around the fact that choice is our constant personal companion. The power of choice is an inextricable part of Self. To pretend it is not is to deny our own existence—impossible to actually accomplish, but we do try it all the time, don’t we.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-what-about----&quot;&gt;But what about . . . ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, groups. Taking language literally can lead us to think of imagined things as being real. For instance, it is convenient to speak of groups as if they make choices, but the truth is that such choices are always, always, always the result of the decisions (or lack thereof) of individuals that constitute the group, even if it is just deciding to “go along to get along” or agreeing to abide by the outcome of a vote, despite disagreeing with the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals might choose to identify with a group concept, or practice a uniform behavior pattern, but they are still individuals. They may choose to be selfish or, on the other hand, to sacrifice even their own individual survival for the sake of others or just for the group ideal. But the individual still always chooses, by active choice or by passive acceptance. There is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; some option. Self and choice can be thought of as facets of the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what does all this have to do with the urge towards decentralization? The amusing thing is that the answer is simultaneously “Everything” and “Nothing,” because the very nature of human experience is &lt;em&gt;already decentralized.&lt;/em&gt; That’s the beautiful, perhaps frightening, but completely irresistible, truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; unit of choice is the individual. Choice is decentralized by its very nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;uh-oh&quot;&gt;Uh-oh!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But,” many will say, “you are promoting anarchy!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, not really. I’d have to say that I’m only suggesting that we embrace, rather than deny, this one solid fact and go forward from there, better informed and able to deal more effectively with what we encounter—with humility, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing inherently wrong with centralization on a structural or organizational level. It is one aspect of how things can be organized and is often most appropriate. There can be great advantages in centralizing resources for scale, as in some forms of manufacturing, and a trusted leader with others following her intelligent direction can accomplish many good things that are otherwise unachievable. Centralization only goes really wrong when it fails to nurture and honor the fact that choice is something that only an individual can truly do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither is decentralization always right. Again, it is one of the ways things can be structured or organized. It can have huge advantages in some situations, but can lose effectiveness if too fractured. On an interpersonal level, if individuals insist too strongly on being independent and making all their own decisions, without respect for the rights or needs of others, all manner of counterproductive conflict results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-middle-way&quot;&gt;The Middle Way&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, few wish to live in either extreme. People want respect for the fact that they can and do choose, always. If they are given a good measure of that respect, they don’t find it necessary to assert their independence so militantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the coin, people are much happier when they learn to equally respect the fact that everyone else has the same need. This is empathy, the binder of human society. Greater and greater volumes of research and experience indicate that this is the natural inclination of people. It is mainly serious neglect and abuse, especially in childhood, that cause individuals to be unable to empathize with their fellows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all that aside, we’re still dealing with the fact that you know who I’m talking about when I say “you.” And, whatever emotional response you might feel when contemplating the fact, you know that the ability and inclination to choose is tied up in your very nature. You need no other credentials or intellectual mastery to evaluate what I’m saying here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;and-decentralization&quot;&gt;And Decentralization?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are we left with regarding the itch or craving for decentralization?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, I think we have to acknowledge and properly value the basic truth that, in human experience, the power of choice or decision is a characteristic of the individual. Individuals have many rational reasons and desires to create and seek identity with groups. There can even be a sense of Self invested in groups, but it seems plain that that sense is felt by individuals in harmony, not separately by some superior entity. But even if there is an actual higher Self vested in a group, or even in the universe as a whole, it is still the individual’s choice to surrender to it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group association and cohesion is vital to harmony and prosperity in human society. But these associations become dangerous when the individuals that comprise them forget the truth, and fail to respect the &lt;em&gt;fact&lt;/em&gt; of individual choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And isn’t our social failure to honor this fact what underlies both the itch and the scratching? We sense the truth, but our collective assumptions are at odds with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a true understanding of this in mind, structural and organizational decentralization are just scratchers. Scratch too hard, too desperately, and the flesh bleeds. Let us not forget that the Bolshevik and French revolutions, and countless similar manifestations, have been fueled by that same “itch” or desperate urge for “decentralization,” for righting this wrong which was felt but not understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centralization, in itself, is not the problem; decentralization by itself is not the solution. And the itch will certainly work against us, as it has so often before, if we do not understand, embrace and own the truth underlying it. The salve to completely quell the itch involves an understanding, specifically the understanding that only Self can choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding has a lot of far-reaching ramifications that can be challenging to sort through. I hope you will choose to probe further and see where it leads. And when in doubt, put your feet back on solid ground by remembering that in this very moment, I’m talking to YOU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John Ferguson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Simpleton of Project SAFE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simpleton@safecrossroads.net&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Postscript:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve been podcasting and writing about the SAFE Network for a few months now, and the inspiration for this article kept eating away at the back of my brain the whole time, till I finally put it on the page and worked with it till it was done. It was only after I’d finished it up and I was telling a friend about the subject matter that a further revelation hit me: The inspiration driving me (and others, I think) to bring the SAFE Network to fruition is my understanding that the technology underlying the network’s design is built from the inside out with respect for Self granted to the individual user by default. That in itself is an immensely powerful thing. Add to it the fact that the technology promises to be superior in so many other ways in terms of speed, efficiency, scalability and more, and it’s hard to contemplate the effect it will have on humanity. As I say, this is an afterthought to the article, which easily stands on its own. But I take this opportunity to encourage you to explore Project SAFE for yourself. The ramifications of the SAFE Network, and the open source technology it makes available to mankind for other applications, are more significant than I know how to communicate. Visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://safecrossroads.net&quot;&gt;safecrossroads.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;maidsafe.net&quot;&gt;http://maidsafe.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://safenetwork.wiki&quot;&gt;safenetwork.wiki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://letstalkbitcoin.com/blog/category/safepodcast&quot;&gt;SAFE Crossroads Podcast feed on LetsTalkBitcoin.com&lt;/a&gt; and find out what it’s all about. JF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/257004322&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/07/the-decentralization-itch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/07/the-decentralization-itch/</guid>
        
        <category>article</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
